<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A godlye, and pithie exhortation, made to the iud[ges of Sussex ...] By William Ouerton, Doctor of Diuinitie, and one of the Queenes Maiesties iustices appoynted for the peace vvithin the same countie</title>
            <author>Overton, William, 1525?-1609.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1579</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68527</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18925</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107302</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843004</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843004</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7708</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A68527)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7708)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 675:04, 1578:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A godlye, and pithie exhortation, made to the iud[ges of Sussex ...] By William Ouerton, Doctor of Diuinitie, and one of the Queenes Maiesties iustices appoynted for the peace vvithin the same countie</title>
                  <author>Overton, William, 1525?-1609.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[60+] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Newbery and H. Bynneman,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1579?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D (-all after D6).</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon preached at the assises in Sussex.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 18925a on UMI microfilm reel 675.</note>
                  <note>The copy catalogued has the provenance label of Sir R. Leicester Harmsworth, Bart., pasted on title page, obscuring text. Imperfect; lacks all after leaf D6.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7708:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Godlye, and pithie Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, made to the Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Iuſtices of Suſſex, and the whole Countie, aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled togither, at the generall Aſsiſes.</p>
            <p>By William Ouerton, Doctor of Diuinitie, and one of the Queenes Maieſties Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces appoynted for the peace vvithin the ſame Countie.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PROVERB. 10.</bibl>
               <p>VVhere no Ruler is, there fall the people to ruine and decay.</p>
               <p>But vvhere much counſayle is, there is health and ſafetie.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed by R. Newbery and H. Bynneman.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:7708:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7708:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing occaſion the laſte Lente to be at Eſtgreene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtedde, it was my chance (gentle Reader) to heare a very learned and frutefull Sermon, made the ſame preſent time before the whole aſſembly of the Sheere. I tooke ſuche profit and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of it my ſelfe by hearing it, and heard it ſo generally commended of others, that I could not but deuiſe how to make com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to many, that which was there vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red but to fewe, that ſo the benefite of it might redound alſo to many. I maye per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happes haue blame of the Authour to put it foorth in printe without his knowledge and conſent, but if he knewe howe muche good he did to thoſe fewe that heard him, I truſt he will not be offended, if by my meanes he doe more good to a greate number that hearde him not, but ſhall reade him, for the exhortation is ſo tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered,
<pb facs="tcp:7708:3"/>and the conueyance of it in ſuche ſorte, that though ye can ſpecially applye it but to ſome men, yet ye maye vſe it ſo generally, that it wyll edifye any man. If all therefore ſhall reade it, it wyll pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite all, bycauſe it hathe matter that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth for all. But if thoſe reade it that are Iudges of circuites, and Iuſtices of the peace, or Iurie men, or ſuche other like, that haue anye calling that way, it will profyte ſuche men moſt, bycauſe to ſuche it moſt apperteyneth. And ſurely, I wyſh aboue all other, that Iudges, and Iuſtices, and whoſoeuer they be elſe, that vſe to giue charge to the people, yea, and thoſe alſo that haue the charge gyuen them, ſhoulde alwayes before they goe aboute ſuch buſineſſe, reade ouer and peruſe thys little peece of worke, that thereby they myghte be ſtirred vp to deale more ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly in Gods cauſes, and in matters of Religion, than commonlye they are wont to do, I doubt not, but like good ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect would follow ſuch reading of it, as did
<pb facs="tcp:7708:3"/>then followe the hearing of it. For thys I ſawe, and hearde my ſelfe the ſame tyme, when the Iudges were come from the Churche to the Hall, and were nowe ſette downe, and the Countrey before them, they did not onely imparte to the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude what great fruite and comforte they had receyued themſelues by hearing that Sermon (giuing it a ſingular commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation in the eares of all men, euen from the benche where they ſate) but alſo then tooke occaſion thereby, to gyue a verye quicke, and vehemente charge to the graunde Iurie, yea, and to the Iuſtices themſelues, and to all others that had anye office or authoritie in the Sheere, to looke more narrowly to matters of Religion, than heeretofore they had done, and to endeauoure themſelues by all meanes poſsible, to conſerue the peace and vnitie of Chriſtes Church, and to ſearch out, and ſee puniſhed all that were offenders to the contrary. And to tell you the truth, it did my heart good to ſee ſo graue &amp; wiſe a
<pb facs="tcp:7708:4"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (Iudge GAVDIE by name) to giue ſo carneſt and godly a charge, in God and the Goſpels behalfe, ſuch good frute followed in that good Magiſtrate, by hearing ſo good and godly a Preacher that day. And I would all others that be of the ſame cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that he is of, mighte haue as good ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king heereafter to reade him, as he hadde then to heare hym, that like fruite maye come of it, when oportunitie ſhal ſerue, for the fruite that followed was great. Well, I will not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend the Preacher vnto thee, (I ſhoulde but darken his due prayſes by mine vnſufficient prayſing of him) but I wil co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend thee to the reading of this his worke, and when thou haſt redde it, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend him thy ſelfe as thou ſeeſt cauſe. In the meane time, I wil pray vnto God both for him and for thee, and for vs al: for him, to encreaſe his tale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in preaching: for thee, to enſlame thy zeale in hearing: for vs all, to amende oure negligence in following. And ſo I bidde thee farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy vvelbeloued brother in Chriſt.
<hi>M. M.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:7708:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Precor vos fratres, vt ſpecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemini eos. &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I praye you Breethren haue a good eye to thoſe menne,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 16. <hi>verſe.</hi> 17.</note> or take heede of thoſe menne, vvhich do breede diſcord and diſſention amongſt you, and giue occaſion of offences, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the doctrine that you haue receyued, and eſchue them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is nothing more accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to God: there is nothing more profitable to man: there is nothing more anſwerable to Chriſtian Religion and Faith: there is nothing more auaylable to vertue and good life: there is nothing more requiſite and neceſſarie for al ſtates, whether they be priuate or publike: there is nothyng more amiable, more delectable, more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable,
<pb facs="tcp:7708:5"/>or more commendable in all reſpectes: at a worde, there is nothing that paſſeth all thinges more, than thys one thing, iuſt peace, grounded vppon the true knowledge and feare of GOD. It is not in vayne there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that the Apoſtle héere exhorteth the Romanes, and by them vs alſo, whiche bée nowe preſente, yea, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chriſtians whereſoeuer, that we ſhoulde beware and take héede of ſuche menne as doe bréede diſcorde and diſſention amongſt vs, and gyue occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of offences in the Churche of God: and not only that we ſhoulde take héede of them, and beware of them, but alſo, that we ſhoulde eſchue them, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde them, as authoures of that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, whyche of all other euilles is moſte daungerous, and dothe moſte ſhake and weaken all ſtates of menne, or rather doth beate downe, deſtroy, and ouerthrowe all thyngs whereſoeuer it commeth in place, menne, houſes,
<pb facs="tcp:7708:5"/>townes, kingdomes, countries, nations, and peoples, be they neuer ſo manye, be they neuer ſo greate and mightie. Suche a meruailous miſchiefe is Diſcorde and Diſſention, wherſoeuer it taketh roote, and therefore good cauſe (I ſaye) that the Apoſtle ſhoulde earneſtly admoniſhe vs al to ſhunne it, and auoyde it, and the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors alſo thereof, which doe ſowe it, and bréede it. I pray you brethren (ſayth hée) take héede of thoſe men whych bréede diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde and diſſention amongeſt you, and giue occaſion of offences contrarie to the doctrine that you haue receiued, and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chewe them. But what diſcorde, or what diſſention is it that the Apoſtle here ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of? for there be two kinds of diſcord, there is one kinde that is ſpirituall, there is another kinde that is temporall. Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual diſcorde is, when men are dinided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelues, and diſagrée one from another, in ſpirituall matters, in Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall cauſes, in matters or cauſes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Faith. This is ſpirituall
<pb facs="tcp:7708:6"/>diſcorde. Temporal diſcord is, when men fall oute amongeſt themſelues, and doe wraſtle, or be at warre (as it were) one with another, aboute temporall matters, aboute temporall cauſes and quarrels, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute inturies or wrongs done, or offered to be done, by one man to an other, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching their goods, landes, or lyfe, or ſome ſuch other thing, pertaining to theyr tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall ſtate: this is temporal Diſcorde. Whiche of theſe two therefore doeth the Apoſtle here ſpeake of? If I ſhoulde tell you, that hée ſpeaketh of ſpirituall diſcord, ſuche as riſeth of ſpirituall matters, of Churche matters, or of matters concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; Faith, you would anſwere me, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my text is not for this place &amp; time, nor pertinent to theſe kinde of buſineſſes and affaires which are nowe in hand, but doeth rather belong to Schoole men and Dimnes, or ſome other ſuche Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal perſons, as are to heare and determine in ſuch caſes. If I ſhould tel you, that hée ſpeaketh of temporall diſcorde, ſuch as ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb facs="tcp:7708:6"/>of temporall cauſes and quarrels, or of temporall iniuries and wrongs and ſo forth, you woulde aunſwere me, that it is ſuperfluous at this time, and more than néedes, to ſpeake of any ſuch matter vnto you: for why? ye come for that purpoſe, it is the only or chiefe cauſe of your repayre hyther at this preſent, to heare and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of ſuch controuerſies and quarrels a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men, and therefore I néede not waſte my winde any further therein. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable and worſhipful, which ſo euer of theſe two kindes of diſcorde it be that the Apoſtle here ſpeaketh of, (as in déede hée maye ſéeme to ſpeake of them bothe) you ſhal perceyue, that my text is not imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent to the place and time, nor anye whyt from the matter ye haue nowe in hande. I knowe well ynoughe, that your aſſembly here togither, at this preſent Seſſion now to be holden, is onelye or chieffic for thys cauſe, to ende diſcorde and ſtrife, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue Vnitie and peace, and to reforme in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries and wrongs, whereof the wante of
<pb facs="tcp:7708:7"/>peace &amp; the ſupply of diſcord doth grow. I know I ſay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> this is your purpoſe, and the chief or only cauſe of your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming hither, &amp; yet this I know too, that my matter wil be no let vnto you, but doth and may very wel agrée with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> your purpoſe. For firſt if I ſhal ſay any thing, to the aleying of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral diſcord &amp; diſſentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> furthera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral vnitie &amp; peace, though it be true in déed, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you be come for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame purpoſe, &amp; do meane now to ſit vpon ſuch matters, yet my frendly admonitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by no means hurt or hinder your good purpoſe, being to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſelf ſame matter you come for, nor wil be altogyther néedeleſſe or vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto you y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhal heare it, ſéeing the beſt &amp; wiſeſt man that is, hath néed ſometimes of a friendlye and faithfull admonitor at hys elbow. On the other ſide, if I ſhal ſay any thing to the abandoning of ſpirituall diſcord &amp; ſtrife, or to the aduancement and furtheraunce of ſpiritual vnitie &amp; concord, in this caſe am I alſo to be heard willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye of you, &amp; though in ſome reſpect I will
<pb facs="tcp:7708:7"/>not deny, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> this kind of diſcourſe doeth belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g rather to ſchole me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; diuines, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to you y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> are te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral lawiers, te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall iudges &amp; iuſtices: yet this I muſte tell you notw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> you can not ſo cleane ſhifte off this kind of matter fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you, as thoughe it wer a méere alien to your other buſineſſe, but you muſt alſo haue to do with it aſwel as wyth other matters, &amp; may not eſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge it fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your preſent affaires. For who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> come you to ſerue, come you not to ſerue Chriſt? I think you wil not ſay nay. For God him ſelf ſo ſayth vnto you by his Prophet, <hi>
                  <hi>Eru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimini qui iudicatis terra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſeruite domino in ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more:</hi> Be learned ye that are iudges of the earth, ſerue the Lord in fear.</hi> What Lord is it y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> you muſt ſerue? y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> K? y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Q? the prince of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try wher you dwel, and vnder who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you are ſubiects? ſurely this lord alſo muſt you ſerue I deny it not. But what Lorde doth God here wil you to ſerue, when hée ſaith vnto you, ſerue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord in fear. Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he willeth you to ſerue Chriſt, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other lords L. that other maiſters Maiſter, your
<pb facs="tcp:7708:8"/>Ladies Lorde and your miſtreſſe maiſter, euen the Quéenes Lorde and maiſter, yea the Lord and maiſter of all Lordes, and of all kings, and of all Quéenes, and of all Princes, and of all the Monarches of the earth, or rather Lorde and Maiſter of all the whole earth it ſelfe. For ſo ſayth God alſo a little before in the ſame Prophete: <hi>
                  <hi>Postula à me &amp; dabo tibi gentes in heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem: &amp;c.</hi> aske of me (ſayeth God the father vnto his ſonne Chriſt) and I wil giue thee the heathen for thine inheritaunce, and the vttermoſt partes of the earth for thy poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsion.</hi> Lo here is Chriſte made Lorde of all Lordes, and Lorde and owner of the whole earthe. The earthe, the nations of the earth, and the Kings of the nations, they are all his, they are giuen him for his inheritaunce, they are giuen him to be his poſſeſſion, and he is Lorde of them all. Wherfore whatſoeuer other Lordes you haue, whatſoeuer other maiſters you haue, you muſt ſerue Chriſt as the chiefe Lorde, and as the graunde Lorde and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
<pb facs="tcp:7708:8"/>ouer al other Lords &amp; maiſters. You muſt ſerue him &amp; his Church, &amp; not onelye your prince &amp; country, not only the Quéen &amp; common wealth: &amp; to ſay the truth, I do not ſée how you can well ſerue the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth, except you firſt ſerue the Church, nor how you can wel ſerue the Prince, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept you firſt ſerue Chriſt: For Chriſt is a patterne vnto the prince, &amp; the Church is a patterne vnto the common wealthe to follow. Neyther is that common wealth a good common wealth, or commendable before God, whiche doth not frame and conforme it ſelf after the Church, nor that Prince a good or commendable Prince, which doth not frame and conforme him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe after Chriſt. So then yée muſt haue a chiefe care and a chief regard of Chriſt, and of the Church of Chriſt, and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentlye of all thoſe matters and cauſes which be inſident to Chriſt &amp; his Church. And therefore as you are readie when you ſée your Countrey or common wealth, the ciuill and politique bodie of the realme,
<pb facs="tcp:7708:9"/>to be rente and torne in péeces, one mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber from another by ciuil diſcorde and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention, by warres, by ſtrife and vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, by fraude, by force, by lying in wait one for anothers goods, or landes, or life, and ſo forth, as you are readie in this caſe to loke vpon and lament the afflicted ſtate of your countrey, and to bynde vppe the woundes of the common wealth, which it hath receyued, and to heale and make vp the hoales and breaches, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> rents and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, which you finde in the bodie politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que, as you are readye to repayre and redreſſe wyth all ſpéede the wrackes and decayes that are in the tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſtate, I ſaye, as you are readie to loke vpon theſe temporall matters, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider throughlye of them, and are nowe come hither for that purpoſe. Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo much more, and much rather, loke you vpon the lamentable ſace and countenaunce of Chriſtes decayed Church, looke vppon the déepe and wide woundes of his myſticall bodie, ſo ſoare ſtricken with ſpirituall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde
<pb facs="tcp:7708:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>and diſſention, ſée howe Chriſte is wounded in his bodie, ſée howe the bodye is maymed in his members, ſée howe the members are rent and torne one from an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, ſée howe they are diuided amongeſt themſelues, nay alas, how they are diuided againſte themſelues: ſée what hoales and breaches are made in the poore Church of Chriſte, ſée what ruine and decaye is come vpon the poore flocke of Chriſte, ſée what numbers of poore ſoules are caried away by rauening wolſes, to be deuoured of them, and are euen yet hanging in their chappes, and in their féeth, and being in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> middeſt of their téeth doe not féele theyr owne miſery, nor ſée their owne daunger: ſée howe euerye thing almoſte is (or if you looke not the ſooner to it) ſhortlye will bée tourned vpſide down, topſie turuie: black will be white, and white will be blacke: truth wil be error, &amp; errour wil be truth: good will be euill, and euill will be good: right will be wrong, and wrong wyll bée right, and euery thing wil be as euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:7708:10"/>wil haue it. For we can not abide to draw all one way, be it neuer ſo godly and iuſt, but euery man drawes his owne waye, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man followes his owne fancie, euery man likes beſt his own wil &amp; wit, &amp; no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> likes another, &amp; ſo we rent the Churche, &amp; teare the Temple of God in ſunder wyth our continuall faction and diſcorde. O mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable ſtate, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnitie of Faith is diuided into varietie of opinions, the profeſſion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpel is drawn into proprietie of ſects, the firme &amp; ſtable worde of God is made a flexible noſe of waxe, &amp; euery man thinkes to writh it which way he wil himſelf. And al this (oh ye iudges &amp; iuſtices) all thys is come to paſſe by the ſléepineſſe of Gods ſeruants, &amp; by the watchfulneſſe of Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; his miniſters, the olde and newe ſecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Sciſmatickes, whiche are bolde to attempt any thing, which bluſhe not to ſay and affirme whatſoeuer they liſt (be it neuer ſo falſe) which contend ſtil for victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie though they be ouerthrowen, yea &amp; are readie with blowes to maintain their euil quarrel if they durſt, whoſe ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds you muſt
<pb facs="tcp:7708:10"/>holde, whoſe féete you muſte ſtaye, whoſe mouthes you muſt ſtop, whoſe raſh &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapert enterpriſes you muſte in anye wiſe reſtraine &amp; repreſſe, that they fight not, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they go not, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they ſpeake not any more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God &amp; his trueth with ſuch libertye as they haue don. This is your office, this is your charge, (oh ye Iudges &amp; Iuſtices) this is your chiefe charge, &amp; therefore this ought to be your chiefe care, this ought to be your chief trauel, to heale vp y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wounds of Chriſts miſtical bodi, to ſtop vp y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holes &amp; gappes of his broken decaied Church, to repayre &amp; renew the peace &amp; vnitie of hys houſe, to beat down &amp; deſtroy al Schiſmes &amp; ſects with the aucthors &amp; fautors therof, to vphold, maintain, &amp; further, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al youre diligence, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al your wit &amp; pollicie, with al your might &amp; power, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true, ancient, &amp; ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike religion of Chriſt. This (I ſaye) is your chief charge, this therfore ought to be your chief care &amp; trauel. Wherefore bend your wits erneſtly about it, put your ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly vnto it, vſe your cunning wiſely,
<pb facs="tcp:7708:11"/>exerciſe your aucthoritye ſpéedilye, let no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing paſſe you that may touche you, let nothing be vndone by you, that maye lye vpon you in that behalfe. For you are not come hither to ſerue ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> only, you are not come hither to ſerue your Prince, youre countrey, &amp; common wealth only: but are come hither to ſerue God, you are come hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſerue Chriſt, &amp; you are come hither to ſerue the Lord in fear. This ſeruice god himſelfe biddeth you to doe, and therefore you muſte doe it, and this ſeruice no man nor Prince forbiddeth you to do, &amp; therfore you may do it and néede not doubt to do it: Nay rather, if I miſſe not my markes, or if my memorie fayle me not, it is the very firſt point or part of your commiſſion giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you from the prince, that you ſhould do it, or at leaſt wiſe it is the firſt thing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> your ſelues giue in charge vnto others, to do it, &amp; therfore I ſhall not néede to ſtande anye longer vpon this point, nor to follow it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny further. Only this I will ſay at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vp of this point, that al controuerſies
<pb facs="tcp:7708:11"/>&amp; quarrels are to be anoyded, that al ſtrife &amp; variaunce is to be cut off, that all diſcord &amp; diſſention is to be rooted vp euery where &amp; in all maner of matters, but yet ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in ſpiritual matters, ſpecially in Church matters: for that diſcorde is a ſore diſcord in déede: that is a worme that perceth dée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, that is a cancker that créepeth further into a man, euen into the innermoſt parts &amp; bowels of a man, to the diſtruction both of boldie and ſoule: as for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other, it annoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth our temporall ſtate only, but pearceth not our ſoules, it hurteth vs not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wayes, but rather doth vs good, if a wiſe man haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter in handling. For by outward af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we are inwardly mended, &amp; ar made better to God ward by worldly troubles if we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wiſely &amp; beare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly.</p>
            <p>But nowe bicauſe we are to beate down-al diſcord &amp; diſſention, &amp; to build vp &amp; repaire godly vnitie &amp; peace, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we maye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better aymie at this marke, whereat we muſt ſhoote, let vs ſée whence this diſcorde and diſſention commeth; and who be the
<pb facs="tcp:7708:12"/>chief &amp; principal aucthours of it. You heard before y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there are two kinds of diſcord, te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral diſcord, which riſeth of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, &amp; ſpirituall diſcorde, which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of ſpiritual cauſes. Touching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> former kind, youre ſelues which are beſt exerciſed in ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil affaires, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beſt iudge or geſſe what be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſes of al ſturs &amp; troubles in the ciuill ſtate, &amp; who are moſt likely to be authors and bréeders of the ſame. For mine owne part, as I am now knit in one care wyth you of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth, &amp; haue the lyke charge that you haue, &amp; therfore would be glad alſo to furder any thing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit &amp; aduantage y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, ſo yet being called another way (as you know I am) and this kind of buſineſſe being y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leſſe parte of my calling, I profeſſe my ſelf to haue leſſe ſkil in it, &amp; therfore leaue the great &amp; waighty conſideration of thoſe matters to your ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per wiſdome &amp; experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Only I wil giue you a ſhort view of ſome of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chiefe cauſes or cauſers of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral diſcord &amp; diſſention, &amp; ſo will paſſe from that to the other pointe, which toucheth my calling more properly.
<pb facs="tcp:7708:12"/>Wil you heare therfore in a ſumme what are the cauſes of diſcord &amp; diſſention in the ciuil ſtate? I wil tel you. The extortion y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mighty, the oppreſſion y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is in the wealthy, the vnſatiable deſire of hauing, &amp; vnreaſonable practiſe of getting, which is in both of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, theſe are cauſes of diſcorde &amp; diſſention. The corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſuch as giue bribes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> periury of thoſe that take bribes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> buying of othes in the one, the ſelling of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other, &amp; ouermuch win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king at both of them, theſe are cauſes of diſcord and diſſention. Gréedie ſéeking for law againſt iuſtice, diuelliſh counſell giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for mony againſt law, enuy in the Client, crafte in the Councellour, and a couetous hearte reygning in both of them, theſe are cauſes of diſcorde and diſſention. The impietie of tale hearers, the impunitie of tale tellers, mallice in the one to ſéeke them, falſehoode and flatterie in the other to bryng them, and an euill conſcience in bothe of them, theſe are cauſes of diſcorde and diſſention. Pryde and
<pb facs="tcp:7708:13"/>diſdaine in the higher ſorte, ſtubberneſſe &amp; diſobedience in the lower ſort, lacke of loue in the one, neglect of dutie in the other, &amp; a froward ſtomack in both of them, theſe are cauſes of diſcord and diſſention. The making &amp; repeling of many lawes, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuting and obſeruing of fewe lawes, boldneſſe vnto ſinne in euery ſtate, zeale vnto godlyneſſe in no ſtate, looſeneſſe in the people, negligence in the magiſtrates, a number of Iuſtices, and yet wante of Iuſtice, theſe are cauſes of diſcord &amp; diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Theſe vices therfore, or theſe defects of Vertue, extortion, oppreſſion, bryberie, periurie, enuie in the clyente, craſte in the councellour, unpietie of tale hearers, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punitie of tale bearers, pryde in one ſorte, ſtubberneſſe in an other ſort, many lawes made, fewe lawes executed, the licentious life of the people, the careleſſe ſecuritie of the gouernours, with ſuche other like, theſe vices (I ſay) and thoſe men that are frayghted therwith, theſe vices and thoſe men in whom theſe vices do raigne, are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:7708:13"/>very cauſes &amp; cauſers of all diſcord &amp; diſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of al ſtrife &amp; variance, of all ſtirres &amp; troubles, and finally, of all manner of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order in the common wealth whatſoeuer it be. Héere you haue a ſhort ſumme of the whole, I néede ſay no more. Looke vppon theſe fewe poyntes, and mende them, and you haue mended all. Thus much briefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for diſcord and diſſention in the tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſtate, and in temporall cauſes.</p>
            <p>Now let vs come to the other kynde of diſcord, whiche troubleth the Churche ſo much. And héere is a greate controuerſie or queſtion amongſt men, whence theſe troubles of the Churche ſhoulde ariſe, and who are chiefe authoures of them. And the controuerſie reſteth ſpeciallye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene the Catholikes and vs, I meane the Papiſtes and vs. And héere, when I ſpeake of Papiſtes, you may not take me that I meane euerye one that is not throughly reſolued in euery poynte of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. For there may be many, whoſe eyes God hath not yet opened, but will do
<pb facs="tcp:7708:14"/>when it ſhall pleaſe him, and yet in the meane time, are good ſubiectes to the Quéene, and neceſſarie members of the common wealth, whome we muſt not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe, but pray for. But vnder the name of Papiſtes, I comprehende thoſe whyche cleaue altogither vnto the Pope and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacie, and by open worde and writing, mainteyne the vſurped authoritie of the Biſhop of Rome, contrary to the word of God, and the lawes and Statutes of thys Realme. Betwéene theſe Papiſtes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and vs is all the queſtion, whiche of vs two ſhuld be diſturbers of the Church, we or they. They lay it to our charge, and ſaye, that we are thoſe that trouble the Church, and their reaſon is this, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we beganne to decline from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and to ſpurne againſt the Popes authoritie, all was well ynough, all was quiet at home, all was peaceable abroade, there were no ſtirres nor trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles in the common wealth, there was no diſcord nor diſſention in the Churche, but
<pb facs="tcp:7708:14"/>one vniforme, and generall agréemente, and conſente of all men togither in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, and Faith: but after that we had once reuolted from that Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church, and had ſhaken off from vs the obedience whiche we owe to oure holy father the Pope, then beganne all this diſcorde and diſſention, then began all theſe ſtirres and troubles, then beganne all this hurlie burlie to be in the Churche, and not only in the Church, but in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the worlde where the Churche is planted: then beganne men to fall togy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the eares, then nation and nation beganne to be at warre one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yea, and nations within themſelues beganne to haue ciuill warre and bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhead, to the great diſturbance of all good policie and gouernement, as at this daye we ſée is come to paſſe in <hi>France,</hi> in <hi>Fla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders,</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> &amp; elſewhere, to the great wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der of the world, and al this by our falling fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> &amp; therfore we that are fallen from that Church, &amp; haue ſwarued
<pb facs="tcp:7708:15"/>from it, are the only cauſe of al the ſtirres and troubles now in the Churche, and ſo conſequentlye, of all the ſtirres and troubles that be in the whale worlde. This is their reaſon that they bryng a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, a great reaſon doubtles, marke it well, this it is in fewer words. We are thoſe that haue ſwarued from the Church of Rome, <hi>Ergo</hi> we are thoſe that trouble the Church, and the whole world. Do yée not marke their argument? it is a muche like reaſon, as if the old ſcribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes of the Iewiſh Sinagog ſhould come againe, and ſaye vnto Chriſt, that before he and his Apoſtles beganne to ſpeake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte them, and their authoritie, and to preach againſt their doctrine and traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſo to carrie the people another way, all things were very well, all was quiet with them, there were no ſtirres, no troubles, no tumultes amongſt the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, there was no diſcord nor diſſention in the Churche, nor in Church matters, but all men agréed very well togither, in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,
<pb facs="tcp:7708:15"/>in ceremonies, in traditions, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and ſo forth, all was huſh &amp; peace, (yea forſooth) the Diuell might ſléepe qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly, there was none to wake him, none to trouble his Kingdome: but after that he and his Apoſtles had once ſhaken their holy Mother the ſinagogue, and had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted againſte their abuſes, and defaced their doctrine, and diſcouered their hipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, and ſo by that meanes had blemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed their authoritie and eſtimation: why now the worlde was changed, the people were not as they were wonte to be, they ſhewed not their accuſtomed obedience and reuerence to their olde holy fathers and guydes the Scribes and Phariſes, but beganne to fall from them, yea, and to murmure and grudge agaynſte them, as ſeducers and deceyuers of the people, and all thys came by hym and hys Apoſtles ſpeaking againſte them, therefore he and his Apoſtles were the onely cauſe of all ſtirres and troubles in Iewry. A muche like reaſon alſo, as if wicked Acab ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:7708:16"/>come againe, and ſay to the good Prophet Helias, that before he beganne to open his mouth againſt Iezabel and hir Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lens, and to inueigh ſo veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly againſt Baal, and his ſacrificing Prieſts, Iſraell was quiet ynough, there was no ſtirre amongſt the people, but after that he had ſhaken that Idoll, and had ſhamed and confounded his Idolatrous Prieſts, then beganne to be ſome ſtirres amongſt the people, &amp; therefore it was he that troubled all Iſraell. Theſe were the reaſons which the Scribes and Phariſes and wicked A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chab brought againſt Chriſt and Helias, and I pray you, are they not all one with that which our aduerſaries bring againſt vs? You are thoſe (ſay they) that ſpeake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Churche of <hi>Rome,</hi> and haue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented from it, therfore, you are authours of all ſtirres and troubles in the Church, and in the whole world. May they not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen with the ſelfeſame reaſon conclude as well againſt Chriſt, and ſay, that hée was Authour of all tumults in <hi>Iewry,</hi> &amp; againſt Helias, that he was Authour of all trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles
<pb facs="tcp:7708:16"/>in <hi>Iſraell,</hi> bycauſe the one ſpake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Scribes and Phariſes, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented from their corruptions, the other a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Baall &amp; his Prieſtes, &amp; would not aſſent to their Idolatrie. Surely y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reaſon is all one: but no man (I thinke) will ſay, that Chriſt indéede was the Authour of al tumults in <hi>Iewry,</hi> though he diſſented from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewiſh Sinagog: nor that Helias was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Authour of all troubles in <hi>Iſraell</hi> though he diſſented from Baals Prieſts. And eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo I thinke, no man will ſaye of vs, or at leaſtwiſe can ſay iuſtly, that we are Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours now of all ſtirres &amp; troubles in the Church though we haue diſſented, &amp; do ſtil diſſent from the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> For it is not our diſſenting fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> that bréedes theſe troubles in the Church, but it is the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelfe, which would haue al men to conſent with hir a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpell, &amp; againſt God himſelf, &amp; al Gods forbod. I grant indéede we diſſent fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> but why, bycauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church of <hi>Rome</hi> diſſenteth from Chriſt and his Church. I grant alſo that
<pb facs="tcp:7708:17"/>vpon this our diſſenting from them; much parts taking dothe followe, and of partes taking commeth diſcorde, and of diſcorde oft times enſueth battell and bloudſhead, and much ado. But who are in the fault? we that diſſent from them in their errour, or they whiche will not aſſent vnto vs in the truth? we tell them that they erre, and we proue out of Gods worde howe and wherein they erre, and this forſooth can not they and theirs abide, but are angrie with vs, and reply againſt vs, and héere of commeth all thoſe troubles, and tragicall ſtirres that be now in the Churche. But in the meane time, whiche ſide is it that troubles the Churche? do we trouble the Churche which tell them of theſe things, or do they trouble the Church, whiche can not abide to heare of theſe things? in deede, if telling them truth, or Preaching the Goſpell vnto them, doe trouble them and the world, I muſt needes ſay, that we are thoſe men that trouble them, and that trouble the world. But yet how? not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlie
<pb facs="tcp:7708:17"/>of our ſelues, nor of ſet purpoſe, but (as the Logitians ſaye) <hi>
                  <hi>Peraccidens,</hi> acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentallye,</hi> and by occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, bycauſe they can not abide to heare the truth. For it is not the proper effecte and worke of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, to bring trouble with it vnto men, but rather to bring ioy and peace of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience vnto thoſe that heare it, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace it. And if it happen to fall out other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, as oft times we ſée it doth, the faulte is not to be imputed to the Preaching of the Goſpell, nor to the Goſpell it ſelfe, but to the euill diſpoſition of ſuch men, as can not brooke it, nor abide to heare it. And ſo we may ſay that Chriſt alſo troubled Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and all the world, bycauſe he preached the Goſpell amongſt the Iewes whyche could not abide to heare it, and bycauſe he ſent his Apoſtles abroade into the worlde to preache the ſame amongſt the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, whyche lykewiſe could not abide to heare it. For the preaching of the Goſpell whiche is called of Saincte Paule <hi>Sermo crucis,</hi> the Preaching of Chriſt crucifyed,
<pb facs="tcp:7708:18"/>was vnto the Iewes a ſtumbling blocke or offence, and vnto the Gréekes or Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles it was fooliſhneſſe, and a very vnſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie thing. It was offenſiue to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes, and vnſaucrie to the Gentiles, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they coulde not abide to heare it, and if they heard it at any time (as ſometimes they did againſt their will) it ſéemed vnto them not onely to bée méere diſcorde and diſſention, but alſo it ſéemed to be a very ſword vnto them, and a kinde of warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their ſtate, as in déede after a ſorte it was. For the Preaching of the Goſpell was a ſpirituall diſcorde and diſſention againſte their worldlie vnitie, the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the Goſpell was a ſpirituall warre againſte their carnall peace: the preaching of the Goſpell was a ſpirituall ſword againſt their humane doctrine and traditions, it was a ſworde to cutte away their blindneſſe and ignorance: to cutte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way their hypocriſie and diſſimulation: to cutte away their errour, ſuperſtition, and idolatrie: to cutte away their vaine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping
<pb facs="tcp:7708:18"/>of God, &amp; falſe worſhipping of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols. It was a ſword to rippe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp, &amp; lay the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> open to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, that all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might ſée them, &amp; diſcerne them of what ſpirit they were, how co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit of God, &amp; of Chriſt. And as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Preaching of the Goſpel was then vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes &amp; Gentiles, euen ſo is it ſtill at this day to all carnall and worldly minded men, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> can not abide to heare it, it is a kind of warre vnto them, &amp; a very ſword to their heartes. And in this reſpect is it, &amp; to this ſenſe, that our ſauiour Chriſt, though he were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prince of peace, yet thus ſaith of himſelf in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpell: <hi>
                  <hi>Non veni in mundum vt pacem afferam. &amp;c.</hi> I am not come</hi> (ſayeth he) <hi>into the Worlde to bring peace with me to the worlde, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſend a ſword into it.</hi> Meaning ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he came not to rocke men aſléepe, &amp; to crie peace peace, where was no peace: he came not to crie peace vnto me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in their wickednes: he came not to crie peace vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in their blindnes, in their ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, in their errour, in their ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in their i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrie. &amp;c:
<pb facs="tcp:7708:19"/>he came not thus to rocke men aſſéepe, nor to crye peace to the worlde in theſe things, wherein could be no peace, but hée came rather with a ſword into the worlde to ſight againſt theſe things, and to fighte againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde, bycauſe of theſe things, he came to ſight (as Saina Paule ſayth) againſt rule and power, againſt worldly rulers of the darkeneſſe of this worlde, and againſte ſpirituall craftineſſe in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly things, that is to ſaye, againſte the Diuell, and his ſubtill illuſions: againſte theſe things came he to fight, and not only to fight himſelfe againſt theſe things, but alſo to muſter his Souldioures and Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, his Apoſtles, his Euangeliſts, hys Prophets, his Martirs, and all other good Miniſters and members of his Churche, he came to muſter them (I ſay) and to put them in readines, that they togither with him, yea, and after him alſo, when he was gone, might be ready to make warre, and to fight, not againſte God and his people, but againſt the hipocriticall Scribes and
<pb facs="tcp:7708:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>Phariſes, and the whole Iewiſhe Sina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gog, which ſeduced Gods people, agaynſt the arrogante and vayneglorious Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, whiche ſeduced the Heathen and Gentiles, againſte Antechriſt and his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, whiche ſeduced the whole worlde: againſte theſe (I ſay) and ſuch other lyke, came he and his Apoſtles to fighte. But with what ſworde? not with a temporall ſworde, not with that ſworde whiche the Pope giueth ſo liuely in his Scutchion, where he croſſeth the key with the ſword, and ioyneth them togither in his armes, ſignifying thereby, that not onely ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall iuriſdiction is committed vnto him, but alſo that he hathe the power of the temporall ſworde in his hande. Chryſte and his Apoſtles came not to fight wyth thys ſworde, nor with fire, nor with fag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got, nor with hatchet, nor with halter, wherewith the Pope hathe murthered a great number of the good Saincts and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of God, nor to make any ciuill war or tumults amongſt the nations, whereof
<pb facs="tcp:7708:20"/>the Pope hath alway bin a great author: Chriſte (I ſay) and his Apoſtles came not to fight with any ſuch ſword, nor after a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch ſorte, but he came to fight with a ſpirituall ſworde, with preaching of the Goſpell, and with the word of God, which of Sainct Paule is called the ſword of the ſpirit, <hi>Take vnto you</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the ſword of the ſpirite, whiche is the worde of God.</hi> This therefore is the ſword that Chryſte brought into the world, this is the ſworde that he fought withall againſt the world. So then you ſée now, that Chriſt alſo him ſelfe troubled the worlde after a ſorte, but yet you heare how he troubled it, you ſée that he vſed the ſworde, and foughte wyth the ſworde, but you heare what ſworde it was that he fought withal: you ſée that he himſelfe broughte diſcorde and diſſention with him into the world, but you beare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte whome, and againſte what hée brought it. And eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo we likewiſe, whom they accuſe, to be troublers of the worlde, we confeſſe of our ſelues indéede, that we
<pb facs="tcp:7708:20"/>trouble the worlde after a ſorte, but yet ſo as Chriſt troubled it: we conſeſſe that we vſe the ſword, and fight with it, but ſuch a ſword as Chriſt himſelfe vſed and fought withall: we confeſſe that we bring diſcord and diſſention amongſt men, but yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch as we ſhoulde bring it, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch as we ought to bring it. We bring not diſcord and diſſention againſte God, nor againſt Chriſt, nor againſte the Goſpell, nor againſt the word of God, nor againſte the doctrine of the Apoſtles and Prophets, we bring no ſuche diſcord &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention into the worlde, but we bring diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord &amp; diſſention againſt palpable blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe &amp; ignorance: we bring diſcorde &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention againſte errour, ſuperſtition, and Idolatrie: we bring diſcord and diſſention againſt mens doctrines &amp; traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to gods word: we bring diſcord &amp; diſſentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt Papiſtrie &amp; Atheiſme: we bring diſcord &amp; diſſention againſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techriſt and his Kingdome: we bring diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord &amp; diſſentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diueliſh vnitie of
<pb facs="tcp:7708:21"/>Gods conſpired eminies whiche diſagrée from vs in the truth, but ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> agrée amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt themſelues too well in all falſchoode and wickedneſſe, if it may ſerue to their owne filthy gaine and aduantage. Againſt theſe is it that we bring diſcord and diſſention, if it may be called diſcord that is againſte the eninnies of God. But in déede, it is no diſcord at all, or at leaſtwiſe, no ſuch kind of diſcorde, as the Apoſtle héere giueth vs warning to beware of and auoyde, and therefore conſequently, the diſcord which we are charged with, being eyther no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde at all, or no ſuche diſcord as is héere reproued by the Apoſtle, it muſt néedes followe, that eyther we are no authoures at all of diſcorde (as they accuſe vs) or if we be authoures of diſcorde, it is of ſuche as is good and commendable, and ſo yet we are good authoures and commendable authours of good &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendable diſcorde, &amp; authors of ſuch diſcord, as is neceſſary for the Church to haue, and of ſuch diſcord, as without which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpel can
<pb facs="tcp:7708:21"/>not take place, or if it do, cannot long hold and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue. For, if there be no diſſenting from falſhoode and lyes, whiche haue béen, and are, and will be to the worldes ende, ſo long as the Diuell hath to do with the world, if there be no diſſenting (I ſay) fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, doubtleſſe the trueth of the Goſpell can neuer take ſure roote, nor be through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſetled, but will be ſoone ouer-growne, or rather ouerthrowne and weyed downe with the ſtinking wéedes of mants witte, which the Diuell doth ſtill heepe occupy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, with odde toyes and deuiſes of their owne, contrarie to the word of God, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſhake or ſhadowe the trueth withall. So then oure Diſcorde you ſee is no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde, or if it be, it is good and neceſſarre Diſcorde: and thus are we deliuered of that infamie and ſlaunder whiche they bring vppon vs, and are not to be char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in déede with thoſe ſturs and troubles of the Church, whych they name vs to bée Fathers of.</p>
            <p>Well, then what ſhall we ſaye to the
<pb facs="tcp:7708:22"/>matter? ſturres &amp; troubles there are in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church, great diſcord and diſſention there is amongeſt vs, whence ſhall we ſearche for the cauſe hereof? or whome ſhall wée make to be authours of it, that the worlde may knowe them and eſchewe them? we wil go no further, but to the rule that the Apoſtle here ſetteth downe, for tryall of the matter:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I praye you brethren</hi> (ſayeth he) <hi>haue an eye vnto thoſe men, whiche cauſe Diſcorde and diſſention amongſt you, and giue occaſion of offences contrane to the doctrine that you haue receyued, and eſchewe them.</hi> Here is the rule ſette downe.</p>
            <p>Now therfore let vs looke about, and ſée whether we can eſpye where anye diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde is rayſed, or where anye occaſion of offence is giuen, againſte the doctrine which we haue receyned of the Apoſtles. And if we finde any matter that bréedeth anye ſuche Diſcorde, or anye manne, that
<pb facs="tcp:7708:22"/>miniſtreth anye ſuche matter to bréede Diſcorde withall againſte the doctrine of the Apoſtles, lette vs be bolde to ſaye that the ſame matter bréeding ſuche Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde, and the ſame man miniſtring ſuch matter, are the verye cauſes and cauſers of al ſturres and troubles that be nowe in the Churche.</p>
            <p>And here wil it pleaſe oure gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle friendes the Catholickes to giue vs leaue nowe another whyle, to be bolde with them, as they haue bene with vs, and to tel them in their eare, that al this matter will lighte vppon their owne neckes? I wil not holde you long, the time is ſome what paſte, and I deſire of my ſelf to bée ſhorte, and I wyll be the ſhorter, bycauſe I goe not nowe aboute ſo muche to proue matters vnto you whyche you knowe not, as to moue you to the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gente conſideration of thoſe thinges whyche bée alreadye knowen vnto you and there fore néede no proufe. For I
<pb facs="tcp:7708:23"/>will referre it to your own knowlege and conſcience, (if you know any thing at all, or haue heard any thing of God, and of his word) I wil referre it to your own know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, whether it be not mamfeſtly true that I wil ſay of them. And this it is that I ſaye, that they and their matters, that is to ſay: they, and the doctrine which they teach: they, and the bookes whiche they write, do bréede and ingender diſcord and diſſention, doe bréede and ingender occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of offences againſt the doctrine of the Apoſeles, and therefore they and theyr matters do cauſe all thoſe ſturs and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles that be nowe in the Church, and are the very thinges in déede whiche the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle here in this place exhorteth vs to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of, and to eſchewe. And now iudge your ſelues whether this be not true that I ſaye, For (as I tolde you) I will ſaye nothing but within youre owne kenning. Haue they not I pray you brought an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite number of traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s into the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of Chriſte, cleane contrarie to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
<pb facs="tcp:7708:23"/>of Chriſte, and of his Apoſtles? of whoſe deuice was priuate Maſſe, and the propiciatorie ſacrifice of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame? of whoſe deuice was inuocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſaincts? of whoſe deuice was adoration of Images? who broughte in Purgatorie, prayer for the deade, Pilgrimage, or Peregrmation to dumbe ſtockes or ſtones, auriculer Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, Church chaſtitie, Monkiſh vows, and a thouſand ſuch other, if it were wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie the time to reherſe them? Of al whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che notwithſtanding, there is not ſo much as one, that is once named or ſpoken of by the Apoſtles, much leſſe commaunded or commended vnto vs by any doctrine of theirs. And yet all theſe thinges doe they teache, all theſe things doe they preache, and write great volumes of them, and by preaching and writing doe maintaine them to the vttermoſte, thoughe directly againſte the doctrine of the Apoſtles. Whiche thing, as it is a ſnare to the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and doth meruailouſly intangle theyr conſciences, that they cannot tell whych
<pb facs="tcp:7708:24"/>waye to turne them, ſo it is a greate of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence vnto the godly to ſée it, and in déede can not abyde it, but reproue them for it: and hereof co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes the Diſcorde and diſſention that is betwéene vs and them, and all the whole ſturres and troubles that are in the Churche. But now iudge you (as I ſaye) who be the authours of al this, whether we which profeſſe the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell and cleaue to the onlye written word of GOD, and receyue and allowe the dactrine of the Apoſtles, or they, which beſides the Goſpell, and beſides Gods worde, and cleane againſte the Apoſtles doctrine, doe bring fancies and deuices of their owne, and ſtabliſhe the ſame moſte diuelliſhly in the Church of Chriſt, to the great hurte of the ſimple (as I ſayde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) and the grieuous offence of all that bée godlye. Sure I am, that by the rule here of Saint Paul, you muſt néeds iudge them to bée the authours and workers of all this Diſcorde and diſſention, and of all ſtirs and troubles that are in the Church.
<pb facs="tcp:7708:24"/>I will omitte to ſhewe you that they are authours alſo of all other troubles a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade in the worlde, of Diſcorde and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention betwéene Princes, of ciuil warres and tumults, of bloudſhed and murther, of priuie mutinies and open inſurrections a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſtate: although I mighte lay before your eyes manifolde examples and manifeſt proues hereof, euen amongeſt our ſelues here in England of late dayes, both by theyr Bulles whyche they ſente hyther to diſcharge menne of they loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and obedience vnto theyr ſoueraigne, and alſo by moſte ſpitefull and contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melious bookes, whyche <hi>SAVNDERS</hi> and ſuche others his companions haue written and ſente ouer into the Realme moſte traytorouſlye, to ſtirre vppe the Quéenes ſubiectes, and euen with open wordes to animate them to rebell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt hir owne perſon. Oh, theſe be fitte guydes to gouerne the Church. But I wyll omitte (I ſaye) to ſpeake of theſe things vnto you, I wyll referre you ouer
<pb facs="tcp:7708:25"/>to the Cronographers whiche haue noted the facts and geſts of euery age and tune, and ſpecially to thoſe which haue written of the practiſes of Popiſhe Prelates, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Eccieſiaſticall hiſtorie or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: althoughe what néede you to ſéeke any further for the things whiche you are der youre owne eyes, and whiche you are already by dayly experience welacquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with, and too well in déede, if it were Gods will. Let them goe, you ſée well y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noughe what they are.</p>
            <p>But nowe there be other ſects beſides theſe whiche doe verye muche trouble and diſturbe the Churche, and ciuill ſtate, as Anabaptiſtes, Libertines, and ſuch other like, which wold haue no common wealth at al, but yet all thinges common, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the woulde haue no Rule nor Maieſtracie amongeſt the people, but yet woulde rule and raigne aboue Magiſtrates, whyche woulde haue no lawes, but yet woulddo what wrong they liſte contrarie to lawe, of which ſorte are thoſe that ſticke not to
<pb facs="tcp:7708:25"/>teache out of open Pulpits, &amp; to beare me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fondly in hande, that it can not be found within the two claſpes of the Bible, that Chriſtian men may goe to lawe, or ſue one an other. And what elſe is this I praye you, but to ouerturne all policie and gouernement, and to haue no common wealth at all? For if we maye not vſe the lawes, we muſt haue no laws, if no laws, then no Magiſtrates, if no Magiſtrates, then no obedience, if no obedience, then no order, if no order, then (as I ſaide) no common wealth at all, but euerie manne maye liue after his owne common wil, as he liſte hymſelfe, and as his owne ſpirite ſhall moue him, whyche is the ſtincking opinion and derie ſinke in déede of al Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſtrie. Such men therfore muſt be loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vpon. And I am afraid leaſt the Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans alſo (as you call them) an other ſects lately ſprung vppe amongeſt vs, doe ſmell ſhrewdly of this ill fauored ſmoake. Of whome, and of others I thoughte
<pb facs="tcp:7708:26"/>to haue ſpoken more, but the time cuttes me off. And of ſome of theſe ſects, there be amongſt your ſelues that knows ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more than I doe, and therefore you ſhall not neede mine inſtruction therein. I will therefore drawe nowe to an end. You haue hearde ſufficiently (as I truſt) whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce all Diſcorde and diſſention commeth, and who be the Authours of all ſtirres and troubles both in ciuill matters touching the ciuill ſtate: And alſo in matters of the Church, touching the ſtate Eccleſiaſtical. The former kinde I deliuered vnto you in a ſumme, and gaue you only a ſhort viewe of it, but yet ſuch as doeth imply in it ſelfe a ſufficiente conſideration of youre whole charge in that behalfe. The other kinde I handled ſomewhat more at length, and declared vnto you plainlye and perticular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly who be the chiefe Authours of Diſcord and diſſention, and of all ſturres and tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles in the Church, namely, the Papiſtes, the Anabaptiſtes, the Lybertines, the
<pb facs="tcp:7708:26"/>Puritanes, and ſuche other like ſectes, the ſeuerall diſcourſes whereof, I thinke I ſhall not néede to recommende vnto youre memories by anye new repeticion neither doth the time ſuffer it.</p>
            <p>This only nowe reſteth (O ye iudges and Iuſtices and the reſidue that are here aſſembled togither to this preſent Seſſion) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> you haue a good care, as I doubt not but you haue, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpéedie redreſſe of al things that are amiſſe, but ſpecially of diſcord and diſſention, whiche whereſoeuer it be there can be nothing but amiſſe. For it is the roote of all euill, and the ſpring of all miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe. Wherefore apply your ſelues, (I beſéeche you) euerye manne in youre or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and degrée, to the appeaſing of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies and ſtrife, laboure what you can to alley Diſcorde and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention in all manner of matters and amongeſt all manner of ſtates, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde and Diſſention amongeſt Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall menne, Diſcorde and diſſention
<pb facs="tcp:7708:27"/>amongeſt Spirituall menne, diſcorde in youre policie, diſcorde in oure miniſterie, diſcorde in the common wealth, diſcorde in the Churche, and ſpeciallye the diſcord that is in the Church. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth to the annoyance of your temporal ſtate, but this exte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loſſe of eternall life, there is a greate oddes therfore betwene theſe twoo, both are to be regarded, but yet the one is to be preferred aboue the other, ſo muche as Golde is to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred aboue Siluer, ſo much as the ſoule aboue the bodie, as Heauen aboue Earth, as euerlaſting thinges aboue thinges mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentanie and corruptible. Wherefore haue a care in Gods name for youre ciuill ſtate, and for the common wealth, and for youre Countrey, but haue a ſpeciall care for your Spirituall ſtate, whiche is the health of youre ſoules, and for youre Spirituall common wealth, whiche is the Churche of Chriſte, and for youre Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Countrie whiche is Heauen aboue. For you are but Pilgrims here in Earth,
<pb facs="tcp:7708:27"/>&amp; ſtrangers in this vale of duſte and claye, neither haue you any permanent houſe or citie here in this worlde, as the Apoſtle ſayth: but your citie is the Celeſtiall Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem on high, and there muſt you build your habitation, there muſte you builde your houſes, if you thinke to dwel and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habite for euer. Deſpiſe not youre houſes here on earth, nor your goodes, nor youre landes, nor youre liuing, nor your life, for theſe are the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral giftes of God, yea, &amp; good giftes of God to, if they be not ill v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: Deſpiſe them not therefore (I ſaye) builde theſe thinges vnto youre ſelues, in the name of God, builde you houſes, build you cities here on earth, builde goodes, builde landes, builde liuings vnto youre ſelues, builde your temporal ſtate here, yea, and builde ciuill peace and vnitie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt your ſelues for the conſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and continuaunce of youre temporall ſtate, no manne ſayes you nay, they are thinges lawfull to be done, yea, and they are well done of you, ſo that you do them
<pb facs="tcp:7708:28"/>iuſtlye and truely and in the feare of God and without iniury or wrong vnto others: but yet lette your chiefe buylding be in heauen and of heauenlye things, buylde vpon the true religion of GOD, buyld vpon the broken bodie of Chriſte, buylde vpon the peace and vnitie of his Church, buylde vppon youre ſelues into his Churche and into his bodye, whereof youre ſelues are members, as well and as muche as anye others, who ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they be that beare the greateſt names and titles of the Church, buylde theſe thynges (I ſaye) and laye youre heades and handes togyther vnfay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedlye to plucke vppe by the rootes all Diſcorde and Diſſention, whyche is a lette vnto thys buylding. And for as muche as the effecte canne neuer ceaſe excepte the cauſe be firſte taken awaye, firſte therefore take awaye the cauſes of Diſcorde and Diſſention out of bothe ſtates ciuill and Eccleſiaſticall, and the
<pb facs="tcp:7708:28"/>thing it ſelfe will ſoone vaniſhe awaye. Remoue from the common wealthe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortion, oppreſſion, briberie, periu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, with ſuche other like vices, and puniſhe thoſe perſons that offende ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, according to the lawes and ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of this Realme, and you ſhall ſée all Diſcorde and diſſention in the ciuill ſtate will ſoone come to an ende. Remove from the Church Papiſtry, Anabastiſtry, Atheiſme, Puritaniſme, with ſuche other Hereticall ſectes, and puniſhe thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that offende therein according to the lawes and ſtatutes of the realme, and you ſhall ſée all Diſcorde and diſſention in the Churche and in Churche matters wyll ſoone come to an ende. And bycauſe euerye man hath his office and authoritie from GOD by meaſure and limitation, ſome more, ſome leſſe, ſome one way, ſome another waye, lette euerye manne haue a ſpeciall eye vnto that charge whyche is principallye incidente to hys
<pb facs="tcp:7708:29"/>his office and callyng, lette hym en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire that ſhould enquyre, let him preſent that ſhoulde preſent, lette him ſpeake that ſhoulde ſpeake, let him heare that ſhoulde heare, let him iudge that ſhoulde iudge, lette him execute, that ſhoulde execute, and ſo forth, lette euerye manne doe that whiche ſpeciallys apperteyneth to his office, and lette him doe it in the feare of GOD and wyth an vpright heart, diligentlye and faithfullye, and we ſhal ſée all that is amiſſe will ſoone be amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. But I feare there is many a one comes hither <hi>pro forma tantùm</hi> (as they ſay) for faſhion ſake only, and to fil vp the Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, but howe to diſcharge their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is the furtheſt part of their thought, yea they thinke not once of it at al. Do ye not thinke that you might finde manye neſtes of ſhrewd ſtinging waſpes lurking in corners aboute you, if you would ſéeke for them. Naye rather do not wée thinke that you knowe alreadie where they are if you woulde vtter them? Ah
<pb facs="tcp:7708:29"/>remember whome you come here to ſerue? not man only, from whoſe eyes you maye hide many things, but God, who ſéeth into the ſecretes of youre heartes, and from whome you can conceale nothing. Looke therefore well aboute you, dallie not with God, he will not be playde withall, goe through with the matters yée take in hand, and hault not for any reſpect, eyther of pleaſing, or diſpleaſing of man, but ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to pleaſe God by your true and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſeruice at this time, as you wil thinke to cléere your ſelues in that day, when you ſhall ſtande before the tribunall ſeate of Chriſte, to render accompte of youre do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. Looke therefore more narrowly to Gods matters, and to Gods cauſes, ſearch out, preſente, and puniſh ſuch erceſſes and defaultes, as be committed againſte the ſtabliſhmente of Gods true Religion, and the quiet ſtate of his Church. Iwis Iwis there are many curſt Calues of Baſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade, whiche ſince they ſuckte the Bull that came from <hi>Rome,</hi> haue giuen ouer all
<pb facs="tcp:7708:30"/>obedience and allegiance both to God and the Quéene. For before that time, they coulde be contente to come to the Churche and to heare Sermons, and to receyue the Sacramentes, and to vſe common Prayer with the reſt of the congregation of Chriſte, and ſo forthe. They were conformable in all reſpectes, and contente to doe anye thing that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéemed good Chriſtians to doe, but ſince they ſuckte that madde Bull, they are become euen as brayneſicke Calues, frowarde, ſtubborne, diſobediente in worde and déede, not to be ledde nor or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by any reaſon, and I would it were no worſe. And yet theſe forſooth can not be ſéen nor heard of when time of refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation is: they can not be heard of at the quarter Seſſions, nor nowe at theſe ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Seſſions, nor when anye commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is ſitte vpon for the redreſſe of ſuche matters, they can not bée eſpyed, or heard of at any ſuche tyme: but when the Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions are paſt, we can both heare and ſée
<pb facs="tcp:7708:30"/>that they haue their open méetings and ſolemne feaſtings togither, ſometimes at one houſe, ſometimes at another houſe amongſt themſelues with all fréedome, and libertie, yea, with all ioylitie and lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtineſſe, talking and ieſting at their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, of the ſtate and of Religion, and ſo forth, whatſoeuer they liſt, to no good end I warrante you, nor withoute vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie meaning: As of late you hadde ſome experience of it Weſtwarde, I pray God ere it bée long, we haue not lyke experience héere Eaſtwarde, and all through oure owne ſiackneſſe and negligence, in looking to theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
            <p>Well, nowe I conclude: Scrue GOD, ſerue hys Churche, and haue an eye to thoſe men that bée enimies and diſturbers of it, and ſo ſeruing God and his Churche, you ſhall ſcrue youre Prince and Countrey neuer a whitte the leſſe, but rather you ſhall ſerue them a greate deale more, and
<pb facs="tcp:7708:31"/>a great deale the better. For to ſerue God and his Churche, is the very head and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of youre whole ſeruice that you now come for, and without that, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer otherwiſe you doe, it is but headleſſe ſeruice, yea, it is no ſeruice, neyther can you ſerue youre Prince and Countrey at all, except you firſt ſerue the Church. And your ſelues as you are Chriſtian men, are this Churche, and the Quéene as ſhe is a Chriſtian Quéene, is the head of thys Church nexte vnder Chriſte. And therfore maruell not, that I ſay vnto you, you can not ſerue youre Prince and Countrey, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept you firſt ſerue the Churche, whereof ſhe is the head, and you the members.</p>
            <p>The God of all grace and of all mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, ſo diſpoſe our heartes, ſo direct oure counſels, ſo gouerne oure actions, ſo fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther oure attemptes, ſo bleſſe and proſper all our doings at this time, and finallye, ſo finiſhe the good worke that we haue nowe taken in hand, and begun in his name, that we maye iuſtly and truly ſerue him, that
<pb facs="tcp:7708:31"/>we may iuſtly &amp; truly ſerue his Churche, that we maye ſerue the Quéene, that we may ſerue the common wealthe, that we maye ſerue one anothers furne in ſuche ſingleneſſe of heart, and true brotherly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, that there maye be long peace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, and one godly vnitie and vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie both of Religion and life, to the glory of his holy name, and the common comfort and ioy of vs all. God our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly father graunt this mercy vnto vs for his ſonne our ſauiour Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſtes ſake, to whome with the father and the holy Ghoſt be all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour &amp; glory now and for euer. <hi>AMEN.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprinted at London by Ralph Newberie, and Henry Bynneman.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:7708:32"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:7708:32"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
